Guide to the Henry Harris Jessup Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Harris Jessup Papers
1851-1912
RG 117
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(10 boxes)
Correspondence, journals, diaries, writings, photographs, and collected material document the missionary work of Henry Harris Jessup and his wife Theodosia Davenport Jessup in Syria. Henry Harris Jessup (1832-1910) was a missionary in Syria from 1856 to 1910, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions and Presbyterian Mission Board. He was one of the founders of the Syrian Protestant College, later known as the American University of Beirut.
Jessup, Henry Harris, 1832-1910
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1832 Apr 19 Born in Montrose, Pennsylvania
1851 B.A., Yale
1855 B.D., Union Theological Seminary
1855 Ordained as Presbyterian minister
1856-1860 Served in Tripoli, Syria as a missionary under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; developed expertise in Arabic language
1857 Married Caroline Bush while on visit to America; --Children: Anna, William, and Henry
1858 Returned to Tripoli
1860 Moved to Beirut
1862 Brother, Samuel, went to Syria as missionary for the American Board
1860 Wife, Caroline, died
1866 One of the founders of the Syrian Protestant College, now the American University of Beirut
1868 Married Harriet Elizabeth Dodge who died in 1882--Children: Stuart, Mary, Amy, Ethel, Frederick
1870 Syrian mission work transferred from the American Board to the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions; Jessup was acting pastor of the Syrian Church of Beirut and secretary of the Asfuriyeh Hospital for the Insane from its foundation.
1873 Published The Women of the Arabs
1874 Published Syrian Home Life
1879 Published The Mohammedan Missionary Problem
1884 Married Theodosia Davenport Lockwood
1891 Published The Greek Church and Protestant Missions
1898 Published The Setting of the Crescent and the Rising Cross
1910 Published Fifty-Three Years in Syria
1910 Apr 28 Died in Beirut
Scope and Contents
These papers are a valuable source of information about American missions in the Near East during the second half of the nineteenth century.
The bound copy books of Jessup's outgoing correspondence in Series I date from 1860 to 1899. Some of the letters in the bound volumes are illegible due to deterioration of the ink; preservation microfilm copies of the bound volumes have been made.
The first two journals in Series II date primarily from before Jessup's missionary service, though the volume covering the period 1855 Jan-Dec includes copies of printed letters by Jessup dating from January 1856 to July 1858. Of considerable interest are two journals documenting Jessup's first voyage from New York to Syria. This series also includes a journal by Jessup's son William, dating from October 1886 to March 1888.
The Pocket Diaries of Series III are of briefer, non-narrative format. Nineteen diaries of Jessup's wife Theodosia document her life as a missionary wife in Syria from 1885 to 1905. Five diaries of Henry Harris Jessup date from 1860- 1862, 1868, and 1882, while one volume, dated 1912, is of Jessup's son William.
The Writings of Series IV relate to personal reminiscences of Jessup, his autobiography Fifty-Three Years in Syria, and the history of the Syria Mission 1860 to 1880. The Photographs of Series V are largely those used in Jessup's autobiography. The Printed Material of Series VI consists of a scrapbook of newspaper clippings dating from 1868 to 1880.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1860-1899
II. Journals, 1853-1888
III. Pocket Diaries, 1860-1912
IV. Writings, 1851-1906
V. Photographs, ca.1870s-1910
VI. Printed Material, 1868-1880
Missions -- Syria; Jessup, Henry Harris, 1832-1910; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; American University of Beirut; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A -- Missions -- Syria
- Correspondence, 1860-1899; Series I
  - Bound volumes
    - Copy book of H. H. Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1860 Jul 14-1861 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1862 Apr - 1863 Feb (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1865 Nov - 1866 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1866 May - 1867 Jan (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1867 Jul - 1869 Jun (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1868 Feb - Aug (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1869 Jun - 1870 Jul (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1870 Jul - 1871 Jul (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1872-1873 May (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1873 May 24 - 1874 Oct 31 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1890 Jan - 1891 Mar (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1891 Dec 21 - 1893 Jun 6 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1893 - 1896 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1897 Jun 21 - 1898 Jul 7 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Copy book of Jessup's outgoing correspondence, 1898 Jul 9 - 1899 Sep 21 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Unbound manuscript correspondence
    - H. H. Jessup to family and friendst, 1856 (Box 11, Folder 57)
    - H. H. Jessup to family and friends, including "journal letters", 1857 (Box 11, Folder 58)
    - H. H. Jessup to family and friends, including on voyage from America to Syria, 1858 (Box 11, Folder 59)
    - H. H. Jessup to family and friends, James R. Spalding to Jessup, 1859, 1860, 1863 (Box 11, Folder 60)
    - H. H. Jessup to family and friends, 1865, 1867, 1868 (Box 11, Folder 61)
    - H. H. Jessup to daughter Anna; son Frederick to H. H. Jessup; Frederick to Anna; Mary Eddy to Anna; Samuel Jessup to Anna, 1882, 1910, 1911, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 62)
    - Notes and fragments (Box 11, Folder 63)
  - Printed letters
    - Letters from H. H. Jessup printed in unidentified newspaper, 1856 (Box 11, Folder 64)
    - Letters from H.H. Jessup printed in newspapers, including the Independent Republican, Montrose, 1857-1859, 1874 (Box 11, Folder 65)
- Journals, 1853-1888; Series II
  - HHJ: one volume, 1853 Jul 31-Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - HHJ: one volume handwritten letters, 1855 Jan 1 - Dec 22; plus copies of printed letters from 1856 Jan 20 to 1859 Jan 4, 1855 - 1859 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - HHJ: Journal of first voyage to Syria - "Personal Journey from Sept. 21, 1855 to Arrival in Syria on Feb. 7, 1856, 1855 Sep - 1856 Feb (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - HHJ: "Journal of a voyage from Boston to Smyrna, Dec. 12, 1855 to Jan. 22-27, 1856, written on board The Sultana in storm and calm", 1855 Dec 12 - 1856 Jan 27 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - William Jessup (son of HHJ): one volume (written from Princeton, N.J.), 1886 Oct-1888 Mar (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Pocket Diaries, 1860-1912; Series III
  - HHJ: Pocket diaries and enclosures, 1860, 1861, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - HHJ: Pocket diaries, 1868, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Theodosia Davenport Jessup: Pocket diaries - nineteen volumes (missing 1894 and 1904), 1885-1905 (Box 7, Folder 23-27)
  - William Jessup: Pocket diary, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Writings, 1851-1906; Series IV
  - Manuscript drafts
    - Volume "R" - Personal Reminiscences (pp. 1-50, Union Theological Seminiary, 1852-1855; pp. 51-68, Trip to Syria, 1855 Sep 21-1856 Feb 7), 1853-1856 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Volume "B" - Personal Reminiscences, 1851 Sep -1855 Sep (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Volume "C" - Personal Reminiscences and Syria Mission History, 1855 Oct - Dec (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Volume "E" - History of the Syria Mission, 1860 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Volume "K" - Reminiscences, 1862-1866 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Miscellanies, 1873-1874 Jan (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Syria History, 1874 Jan - 1887 May (Box 8A, Folder 35)
    - Volume "M", 1887 - 1893 (Box 8A, Folder 36)
    - Volume "N", 1894 Jan - 1899 Dec (Box 8A, Folder 37)
  - Related to HHJ autobiography: Fifty-three Years in Syria
    - Introduction and Conclusion (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Sequelae of the Massacres, 1860 Sep (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Untitled notes, writings, 1874 - 1893 (Box 9, Folder 40-41)
    - The American Palestine Exploration Expedition, 1873 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Presentations, Furloughs; "Arthington, Antonius Yanni - A Sketch", 1870 Mar (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Untitled notes, writings, 1894 - 1906 (Box 9, Folder 44-46)
    - fragments, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 47-49)
- Photographs, ca.1870s-1910; Series V
  - Individuals - missionaries, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Individuals - Middle Eastern, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Churches in Syria/Lebanon, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Mission schools and orphanages in Syria/Lebanon, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Scenery and buildings in Syria/Lebanon, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Scenes of everyday life in Syria/Lebanon, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - Unidentified photos, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Prints of photographs on large pieces of paper, ca.1870s-1910 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Inventory lists of photographs and other papers (Box 10, Folder 58-60)
- Printed Material, 1868-1880; Series VI
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1868 - 1880 (Box 10, Folder 61)